Nicholas, Spyrison, Ph.D.

Machine Learning | Dimension Reduction

Parker, CO 80134 (720) 765-1836 nspyrison.netlify.com/ github.com/nspyrison in linkedin.com/in/nspyrison/



Career Summary

A published data scientist with years of experience hypothesis testing, experimental design, enterprise-level reporting, and machine learning on a diverse range of data. Conducted end-to-end development on multiple R packages delivering open-source solutions to the community. Nick frequently acts as a mentor to sharing best practices with the team resulting in continuous improvement, performance code, and increase project completion.

Employment History

06/2022 - 01/2023 Research Data Scientist, University of Queensland,

Clayton, VIC.

- Lead end-to-end analysis of the largest global COVID-19 patient-level data resulting in several submitted journal articles on kidney health outcomes
- Delivered batteries of models varying cohorts, model formulas, and hyperparameters tuning on patient-level health data

07/2018 - 10/2022

Research Officer, Monash University,

Clayton, VIC.

- o Data Fluency Instructor: Lead workshops (10-30 people) on statistical modeling, R, Python, PowerBI, and Git
- o Teaching Assistant: Post-grad tutorials on high-dimensional data analysis, post-grad data visualization, business and undergrad economic statistics
- o Research Officer: Extract, transform, load, and analysis of census and text data

12/2016 – 1/2018 Business Intelligence Developer, CPI Card Group,

Denver, CO.

- SQL reporting; across 4 reporting platforms and 4 severs
- Mentor junior teammates and improve query performance
- Triage and transfer 30+ legacy reports to modern reporting solution
- Developed supply chain report tracking a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD

07/2015 - 10/2016 Business Intelligence Developer, UDR Real Estate Investment Trust,

Denver, CO.

• Transition enterprise reporting from WebFOCUS to SSRS – 10+ reports

11/2014 – 04/2015 Business Intelligence Analyst, Heartland Financial USA,

Dubuque, IA.

• Financial reporting for internal and external audiences

02/2013 - 05/2014 **Delivery Analyst**, *IBM - International Business Machines*,

Dubuque, IA.

- Automated ETL with VBA macros for about 0.5 FTE savings across the team
- KPI reporting to teams and management

01/2010 - 08/2012 Laboratory Technician, The Ames Laboratory & Iowa State University,

Ames, IA.

Authored Software (R Packages)

09/2022

cheem – Novel analysis and interactive visual for exploring ML interpretability

10/2020 spinifex – ggplot2-like API for composing and exporting animated projections Link Link

Education

02/2018 - 06/2022 Ph.D. Information Technology & Statistics, Monash University, Clayton, VIC, Dimension reduction, interactive and animated data visualization, machine learning

Thesis: Interactive and Dynamic Visualization of High-dimensional Data.

- Novel interoperability visualization methods for Fit random forest models on several contemporary datasets also shown to generalize to other models with SVM and XGboost
- o Utilized SHAP and LIME local explanations to explore local linear variable importance to understand large residuals in the models
- Created **novel interactive animation** facilitating this exploration in a web app
- Authored an R packages on CRAN as free and open source work in improve reproducibility and contribute back to the community

08/2008 - 05/2012 B.Sc. Statistics, Iowa State University, minors in Physics and Mathematics, Ames, IA.

Technical Skills

Programs R, SQL, Python, Git, GitHub, LaTeX, Excel, VBA

Packages ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, keras, pandas, scikit-learn

Reporting SSRS, Tableau, PowerBI, Rmarkdown, Shiny

Awards and Honors

06/2022	Invited article for INFORM's OR/MS Tomorrow	<u>Link</u>
04/2022	RStudio: March "Top 40" New CRAN Packages	<u>Link</u>
05/2022	Monash Postgraduate Publication Award	
10/2020	Melbourne Datathon 2020 – 1st place of several hundred entries	<u>Link</u>
	o Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions	S
11/2018	ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award	
07/2018	UseR2018 Datathon – 3rd place	
	 Spatio temporal animated visualization of over 7 million avian sightings 	
2018 – 2022	Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship	
2018 – 2022	Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship	
05/2012	Nominated for Student Employee of the Year	
05/2011	Nominated for Student Employee of the Year	

Publications

05/2008 American Legion Award

Doctoral Thesis

Nicholas S Spyrison. "Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. PhD thesis. [1] Monash University, Mar. 2022. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/thesis_ns/blob/master/ docs/thesis_ns.pdf.

Journal Articles

- Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. "spinifex: an R Package for Creating a Manual Tour of Lowdimensional Projections of Multivariate Data". en. In: The R Journal 12.1 (2020), p. 243. ISSN: 2073-4859. DOI: 10.32614/RJ-2020-027. URL: https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2020/RJ-2020-027/index.html (visited on 10/16/2020).
- [3] Stuart Lee et al. "The state-of-the-art on tours for dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. In: WIREs Computational Statistics (Dec. 2021), p. 21. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: 10.1002/wics.1573. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/wics.1573 (visited on 12/10/2021).

- [4] Nicholas Spyrison, Dianne Cook, and Przemyslaw Biecek. "Exploring Local Explanations of Nonlinear Models Using Animated Linear Projections". In: arXiv preprint, submitted to JMLR (2022). DOI: 10. 48550/ARXIV.2205.05359. URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05359.
- [5] Nicholas Spyrison, Dianne Cook, and Kim Marriott. "A Study on a User-Controlled Radial Tour for Variable Importance in High-Dimensional Data". In: arXiv preprint, submitted to TVCG (Dec. 2022). arXiv:2301.00077 [stat]. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2301.00077. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00077 (visited on 01/06/2023).
- [6] Marina Wainstein, Nicholas Spyrison, and et al. "Association of country income level with the characteristics and outcomes critically ill patients hospitalized with acute kidney injury and COVID-19: A multinational study." In: preprint Kidney International submission (Jan. 2023). (Visited on 01/20/2023).

Software (R Packages)

- [7] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. spinifex: Manual Tours, Manual Control of Dynamic Projections of Numeric Multivariate Data. 2021. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spinifex.
- [8] Nicholas Spyrison. cheem: Interactively Explore the Support of Local Explanations of a Model. 2022. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cheem.

Conference Proceedings

- [9] Nicholas S. Spyrison. "spinifex: visualizing local structure of higher dimensions". en. In: Brisbane, Australia, 2018. URL: https://user2018.r-project.org/poster/ (visited on 07/28/2020).
- [10] Madeleine Barrow, Jieyang Chong, and Nicholas Spyrison. "Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions". en. In: *Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category*. Oct. 2020, p. 4. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/melb_datathon2020/blob/master/_paper/paper.pdf (visited on 02/09/2022).
- [11] Nicholas Spyrison, Benjamin Lee, and Lonni Besançon. ""Is IEEE VIS *that* good?" On key factors in the initial assessment of manuscript and venue quality". In: *IEEE AltVis Workshop*. type: article. July 2021. DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/65wm7. URL: https://osf.io/65wm7/ (visited on 08/21/2021).
- [12] Nicholas Spyrison. "Animated Linear Projections". In: Summer 2022. INFORMS, May 2022.

References available on request.